Women Art Revolution: videotape interviews by Lynn Hershman-Leeson M1639
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Interviews
  - Marcia Tucker
    Marcia Tucker (1940-2006) was a curator and founder of the New Museum of Contemporary Art in New York, an institution she directed for twenty-two years. Both her curatorial practice and her museum held as a philosophical underpinning the notion that contemporary art and its exhibition should be challenging conceptually and, often, politically. Tucker's practice of this belief in the organization of a Richard Tuttle exhibition led, at least indirectly, to her dismissal from a curatorship at the Whitney Museum of American Art in 1977—a development that was her impetus to create the New Museum. In her role as director she oversaw the mounting of such exhibitions as Bad Painting (1978) and Bad Girls (1994), the catalog for the latter of which contained an essay by Tucker titled "The Attack of the Giant Ninja Mutant Barbies." Her engagement with feminist art was sometimes direct (the aforementioned show and her rumored involvement with the Guerrilla Girls being two examples) but often more subtle, an implicit component of her mission to support the radical in art.
    - Santa Barbara, CA; 2006-07-26 (Box 1, Videotape 32A)
      Mini-DV (32A), Digital .mov file
  - Camille Utterback
    Camille Utterback (b. 1970) is an artist and programmer in the field of interactive installation. As she states on her Web site, "My work is an attempt to bridge the conceptual and the corporeal." Utterback's work has been exhibited at galleries, museums and festivals both nationally and internationally. In addition to her own artwork, Utterback heads her own company, Creative Nerve Inc., which develops long term and permanent installations for commercial and museum settings.
    Utterback's awards include a 2009 MacArthur Foundation Fellowship, the Transmediale International Media Art Festival Award (2005), a Rockefeller Foundation New Media Fellowship (2002), and a commission from the Whitney Museum for the CODeDOC project on the Museum's Artport Web site (2002). Utterback holds a U.S. patent for a video tracking system she developed while working as a research fellow at New York University (2004). Her work has been featured in Art in America, Wired Magazine, The New York Times, ARTnews, and many other publications. It is also included in the 2003 publication Digital Art (2003) by Christiane Paul.
    - Unknown Location; 06-2008
  - Cecilia Vicuña
    - New York, NY; 2008-05-01
      The Cecilia Vicuña interview begins at 00:18:58 in the Judith Brodsky digital file.
      Digital .mov files (2)
  - WACK! P.S. 1 Opening
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-28
      Scope and Contents note
      This digital file also includes interviews with Carolee Schneemann and Sylvia Sleigh as well as the DISBAND performance.
  - Faith Wilding
    Faith Wilding (b. 1943) works across disciplines, creating sculptural installations, performances, essays, and monologues as a means to explore the feminine identity in social, psychological, and biological terms. When Judy Chicago and Miriam Schapiro founded the Feminist Art Program—which they began at California State University, Fresno in 1970 and then moved to the California Institute of the Arts (CalArts) in 1971—Wilding was one of its first graduate students. The program’s first major project, Womanhouse (1971-72) was a defining moment in Wilding’s career. Her sculpture Crocheted Environment (1972), installed in one of the house's rooms, formed an archetypal womb-like structure around its viewers, the feminine connotations of which were enforced by her use of crochet in its construction. It is illustrative of Wilding's interest in highlighting women's maternal, domestic, and often communal roles in society—sometimes to complicate or question them, sometimes to celebrate them.
    More recently Wilding has focused specifically upon the ways in which bodies, and particularly women's bodies, are affected by the encroachment of technology upon biology. She has published essays relating to the topic and created works such as Recombinants (1992-96), a set of drawings depicting humans that have melded with machines, plants, and animals. subRosa, an artists' collaborative of which she is a member, creates works relating to biotechnology and women's health, women's representation in politics and the media, and other issues—all relating to what it terms "cyberfeminism."
    - New York, NY; 1990-05-30 (Box 2, Videotape 33A)
      U-matic (33A), Digital .mov file
  - Martha Wilson
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-12 (Box 1, Videotape 34A)
      Mini-DV (34A), Digital .mov file
    - New York, NY, 2008-02-15 (Box 1, Videotape 34B)
      Mini-DV (34B), Digital .mov file
- Transcripts, 53 item(s) (Box 3, Folders 1-46)
  This series includes transcripts for most videos in the collection except:
  Judith Brodsky
  Cornelia Butler 2008
  Beatriz da Costa
  DISBAND performance
  Guerrilla Girls 2008
  Harmony Hammond
  Alanna Heiss
  Yael Kanarek
  Sheila Levrant de Bretteville 2008
  Lucy Lippard
  Rachel Rosenthal
  Martha Rosler 2008
  Carolee Schneeman
  Sylvia Sleigh
  Nancy Spero
  Camille Utterback
  Cecilia Vicuna
  WACK! PS1 Opening
  Martha Wilson 2008
- Digital Storage
  - RAID portable hard drive: WAR Part 1, clone (Box 4, Computer media 2, Computer media 1)
  - RAID portable hard drive: WAR Part 2, clone (Box 4, Computer media 2)
- Transcripts, Working Materials & Documentation
  Scope and Contents
  Working materials and documentation for the film "Women, Art, Revolution," comprising the following files of interviewees. The interview transcripts are sometimes different from and more complete than the edited versions on the Stanford website, in that they include timing marks and identification of edits and other content. The Lucy Lippard transcript is not present on the web site.
  - Eleanor Antin: Image licenses; transcript; slides; release (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Janine Antoni: Image licenses, releases, transcript (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Judy Baca: Image licenses, still photos; postcard, photocopied documentation, transcript (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lynda Benglis: releases (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Judith Bernstein: Image licenses; DVD with images, releases (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Judith Brodsky: Releases (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Connie Butler: Releases, transcript, image license (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Theresa Cha: Image licenses; DVD with images (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Judy Chicago: Image licenses; office correspondence; 3 autograph letters including an important 6 page critique of WAR; release agreements; interview transcript (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Shelia Levvrant de Brettville: Image licenses; releases; tls; transcript (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Beatriz da Costa: photocopied documentation; releases; transcript (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Mary Beth Edelson: Image licenses; DVD with images; related correspondence (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Howard Fox: Releases, transcript, DVD with images (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Susan Grode: Release, transcript (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Guerilla Girls: Carey Lovelace: Release, transcript (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Alanna Heiss: Release (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Barbara Hammer: note, release (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Harmony Hammond: Image licenses; 2 DVDs with cover letters; releases (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Lynn Hershman: Image license (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Amelia Jones: Image license; release; transcript (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Miranda July: Image license, releases, transcript (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Guerilla Girls: Kathe Kollwitz: Image licenses; releases; transcripts, 2 dvds (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Yael Kanarek: catalogue, image license, DVD with images, release (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Mary Kelly: Image license, DVD (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Mike Kelly: Releases, transcript (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Joyce Kozloff: Catalogue, photos, artist ephemera; image licenses, release, transcript (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Robert Kushner: Image licenses, slides, transcript (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Karen Lecocq: Image licenses, 2 DVDs of slides, with list; essay, correspondence (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Leslie Labowitz: Image licenses (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Lucy Lippard: Clip license, transcripts (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Ana Mendieta: Image license (Galerie Lelong) (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Lorraine O Grady: Image license, dvd; photocopied documentation (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Adrian Piper: Release (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Howardeena Pindell: 8 original photos, cover letters, clip and image licenses, DVD; release, transcript, cv (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Suzanne Lacy: Release, image and clip licenses, set of 5 slides "In mourning and in rage" issue of "High Performance," (41/42); photocopied documentation, transcript (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Yvonne Rainer: License, release, artist ephemera (announcements), photocopied documentation, transcript (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Arlene Raven: Release from Video Data Bank (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Maura Reilly: Releases (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - B. Ruby Rich: Release, transcript (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Faith Ringgold: Image licenses, releases, photocopied documentation, transcript (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Martha Rosler: Image licenses, release, DVD with images, transcript (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Rachel Rosenthal: Image license, DVD, release, image list, transcript (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Moira Roth: Releases, transcript (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Betye Saar: Image license, DVD (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Elizabeth Sackler: Release (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Miriam Schapiro: Releases, transcript (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Carolee Schneeman: Photocopied documentation, image and clip licenses, releases (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Lowery Stokes Sims: Release, transcript, image license (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Nancy Spero: Clip and image licenses, releases (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Marsha Tucker: Image and clip licenses, release, transcript (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Mierle Laderman Ukeles: DVD, image license (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Cecila Vicuna: Image and clip license, release (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Hannah Wilke: Image license, release (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Faith Wilding: Imagelicenses, transcript, 1 letter (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Martha Wilson: Image licenses, DVD, transcript (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Nancy Youdeman: Image license, 9 slides, DVD (Box 5, Folder 56)